<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Posts on Data Analytics 6600</title>
    <link>/analytics6600/post/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Posts on Data Analytics 6600</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>&amp;copy; 2018 Slava Nikitin</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 05 Feb 2018 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="/analytics6600/post/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Case Study 3</title>
      <link>/analytics6600/post/case3_ids/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 05 Feb 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/analytics6600/post/case3_ids/</guid>
      <description>Intrusion Detection on Computer Networks Project  Background
A gas utility company XYZ LLC delivers gas to residential and commercial customers across three states. The extraction and distribution infrastructure is computerized, with some computers having public access and others operated by empoyees. The lack of complete isolation of the computer network presents a cyber target of strategic value. The utility is mandated to defend the periphery of the network from the connection perspective, but has no internal monitoring of harmful, intentional or unintentional, activity.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Case Study 2</title>
      <link>/analytics6600/post/case2/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 29 Jan 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/analytics6600/post/case2/</guid>
      <description>Conference Proceedings Analysis Project  Background
A retail company XYZ LLC prides itself on excellent customer service. One way to deliver excellence is by listening to customer complaints about their products and services collected through various channels like email or phone. Upon receiving a complaint, it is supposed to go through a classification process assigning it a product, sub-product and progressively detailed reasons for the complaint. The purpose of the classes is to organize complaints, and enable calculation of descriptive statistics and trending to get a better insight into what needs to be adjusted and how to prioritize work.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Case Study 1</title>
      <link>/analytics6600/post/case1_abstracts/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 22 Jan 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/analytics6600/post/case1_abstracts/</guid>
      <description>Conference Proceedings Analysis Project  Background
A health care company XYZ LLC hosts conferences on novel variants of cancer and technologies meant to detect it early. Scientists in charge of it are responsible for preparing a summary presentation of past and present research. Objectives
Understand origins of authors, co-author network, novel variants of cancer, clusters of abstracts based on similar topics, trends across the last decade in most prominent research topics.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Introduction</title>
      <link>/analytics6600/post/intro/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 08 Jan 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/analytics6600/post/intro/</guid>
      <description>Outline Introductions Analytics as a Layer of Digital Transformations Introduction to R Installation of RStudio Demo of Programming in RStudio   Data Science as a Layer of Digital Transformation   Cycles of Innovation   Problem-Driven Innovation   Analytics Producer:  Roles: Data scientists, software developers, infrastructure engineers, business analysts, subject matter experts Backgrounds: Math/stats, social sciences, economics, computer science Skills: Math/statistics, communications, domain expertise, “end-to-end” Key Attributes: Curiosity, a desire to learn, a willingness to get hands dirty Culture: Work in close proximity, exposure to variety of problems, safe to question, acceptable failure rate   Analytics Client:  Available data and an SME (can someone plug in a laptop and query the data?</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Projects</title>
      <link>/analytics6600/post/guidelines/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 10 Apr 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/analytics6600/post/guidelines/</guid>
      <description>Sections and Rubric You can get total of 60 points for the project. Here is the break down:
Document settings (1 point)
Fix your upper functions. Put the bit of code below at the top of your Rmarkdown document (replace what’s there be default). Note the self_contained and code_folding options. Also, note the indentation, it is necessary for the options to take effect.
title: &amp;quot;Project&amp;quot; author: &amp;quot;Your Name&amp;quot; date: &amp;quot;April 10, 2017&amp;quot; output: html_document: self_contained: true code_folding: hide  Knitting (1 point)</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Wrangle - Part II</title>
      <link>/analytics6600/post/wrangle2/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 20 Feb 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/analytics6600/post/wrangle2/</guid>
      <description>Strings Package: library(stringr)
Creation:
x &amp;lt;- &amp;quot;Richard Stallman doesn&amp;#39;t mind if you read his mail as long as you don&amp;#39;t delete it before he reads it. &amp;quot; y &amp;lt;- &amp;#39;Richard Stallman met Chuck Norris once. Chuck tried a roundhouse, but Richard bashed him in the skull.&amp;#39; Try creating this string
&amp;#39;Richard Stallman&amp;#39;s beard trimmings can cure cancer. Too bad he never shaves.&amp;#39; Escaping quotes to have quotes inside quotes
&amp;#39;Richard Stallman\&amp;#39;s beard trimmings can cure cancer.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Wrangle - Part I</title>
      <link>/analytics6600/post/wrangle/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 13 Feb 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/analytics6600/post/wrangle/</guid>
      <description>Basic Concepts Material  tibble(x = 1:3) local in R data() - local in R  - local on disc  - remote on disk, direct download  - remote on disc, api   Machinery  computer integrated development environment (IDE) programming language file formats   Product  data clean data visualization statistical model report web application optimized algorithm package    Task IO  library(readr) library(tibble)   Tidy  library(tidyr)   Transform  library(dplyr)   Visualization  library(ggplot2)   Programming  library(magrittr)    Learning new packages and functions  CRAN help(package = &amp;quot;readr&amp;quot;) purpose available arguments example code, sometimes demo(package = &amp;quot;stats&amp;quot;), example(&amp;quot;summarise&amp;quot;, package = &amp;quot;dplyr&amp;quot;)   Tibbles Creating  tibble tibble( population = c(783744, 923972, 823972, 789374), city = c(“chicago”, “columbus”, “boston”, “cleveland”) )</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>